Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dick Thornburgh Papers, Series IX. Campaign for Governor of Pennsylvania
1978
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thornburgh, Dick
AIS.1998.30.09
85 Linear Feet
Dick Thornburgh officially kicked off his campaign for Pennsylvania Governor on January 10, 1978. After a Primary victory, William W. Scranton III held the number two spot on the Republican ticket. On the Democrat side the victors were Pete Flaherty, popular former Pittsburgh Mayor, and an improbable school teacher, Robert P. Casey. A masterful campaign strategy was successful, and early evening on election night the Thornburgh/Scranton ticket was seen to win handily. This campaign matched two highly regarded Western Pennsylvanian candidates against each other with full documentation here of both political and issue components. Opposition research includes much information about Pittsburgh during Flaherty's years as mayor. Debate issue and response materials are extensive. All endorsements, for both tickets, are included as well as Thornburgh's ensuing inaugural plans, related photos, and videos. The post-election transition study team reports provide significant insight into priority areas for the new administration. There are twelve sections of campaign files: Speeches and Testimony; News Releases; Endorsements, Responses, and Articles; Campaign in Progress; Issue Research; Opposition Research; Planning Documents and Memoranda; Campaign Name Files; Dickman Files and Polls; Candidate Thornburgh's Files; Chron Files and News Clippings; Transition and Inaugural. There also are five scrapbooks of the campaign with some information not contained elsewhere. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Thornburgh, February 27, 1998
Previous Citation
Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932-, AIS.1998.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Organized crime -- United States; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Personal papers; Politics; Government; Business and Industry; Pennsylvania -- Economic conditions; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania; Environment; Tourism -- Pennsylvania; Pollution -- Law and legislation; Factory and trade waste -- Environmental aspects; Industrial promotion -- Pennsylvania; Economic development projects -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania. Governor -- Elections, 1978; Kirkpatrick & Lockhart; Casey, Robert P. (Robert Patrick); Flaherty, Peter F.; Scranton, William W. (William Warren); Thornburgh, Ginny (Judson); Thornburgh, Dick
- Campaign for Governor of Pennsylvania, 1978; IX.
  Scope and Contents note
  "The opportunity to run for governor in one's home state comes to few people in their lifetime and I was understandably intrigued by the possibility [considering] my long-time interest in public service" (Evidence draft, p. 259). And so it was that upon returning to Pittsburgh in March 1977, following the two years in Washington serving as Assistant Attorney General in charge of the Criminal Division, Thornburgh set out to seek Pennsylvania's governor's office in the following year's election. With the generous encouragement of his law firm, Kirkpatrick, Lockhart, Johnson & Hutchison, which he rejoined, the balance of 1977 was spent assessing his chances.
  A state the size of Pennsylvania is a daunting challenge to statewide candidates. Major hurdles were the financing required and the all-important campaign staff and organization. Thornburgh was lucky in having a college classmate, Evans Rose, Jr., who actually enjoyed fund raising and who successfully did so for this campaign and many other endeavors to follow. His choice of Jay Waldman as Campaign Manager was what Thornburgh describes as a "leap of faith." His "savvy intelligence and strategic insights ... [and] absolute loyalty" (Evidence, p. 76) proved to be remarkable then and over the years that followed. By fall, the hard core campaign organization also included Paul Critchlow, a former political writer for the Philadelphia Inquirer, as Press Secretary; Rick Stafford, a graduate of Carnegie Mellon's Graduate School of Urban Affairs, to head the research team; Jim Seif, who first helped with the 1966 Campaign for U.S. Congress, to take on scheduling; and Murray Dickman, a classmate of Rick's, described by Thornburgh as "our utility infielder" (Evidence, p. 76). These names resound throughout the files from this successful campaign, as well as for the years as Governor, and ongoing.
  The Primary effort included accepting virtually all speaking invitations extended, testifying before a state House subcommittee on crime and corruption in the [Governor] Shapp administration, meeting with GOP leaders around the state, and attending festivals, GOP picnics with new "Thornburgh for Governor" buttons, county dinners, and candidate forums. There was always the hope for increasing press coverage for this lesser-known candidate, whose odds in 1977 were twenty to one according to a Philadelphia Magazine article.
  The official kick off of the campaign came on a snowy Pittsburgh day, January 10, 1978, which was followed by a three-day blitz of the state. Thornburgh's remarks reviewed the unfortunate number of criminal convictions or other wrong-doing of state officials, and further noted: "It is a time for state government to learn to live within its means ... We must recognize that there are limits to our resources. We cannot try to do everything lest we do all things badly. We must do those things which are important and do them well" (Evidence, p. 81). All campaign speeches and position papers are available here online.
  By the time of the primary election on May 16, 1978, Thornburgh was one of five principal Republican candidates. These were: Pennsylvania State House leader Robert Butera of Montgomery County; Pennsylvania Senate Leader Henry Hager of Williamsport; former Philadelphia District Attorney Arlen Specter; and David Marston, former U.S. Attorney for Eastern District of Pennsylvania. The two "fringe candidates" (Evidence, p. 82) were: Andrew Watson, former chairman of the state's Constitutional Party, and Alvin Joseph Jacobson. A series of detailed and meticulously researched position papers were released, endorsements began to proliferate, but at the last, the consensus was that the primary election was "too close to call."
  It was not until after two o'clock on the morning after the primary that victory was declared and William W. Scranton III was found to hold the number two spot on the Republican ticket. On the Democrat side the victors were Pete Flaherty, popular former Pittsburgh Mayor, and the "improbable Robert P. Casey, the Pittsburgh schoolteacher who soon became known, with our assistance, as 'the wrong Bob Casey'" (Evidence, p. 85).
  As the general election got underway, the comprehensive Bob Teeter poll conducted after the Primary showed Flaherty with a thirty-two-point lead - 55 percent to 23 percent! This stunned the campaign, which knew Thornburgh was underdog, but not by such an almost insurmountable deficit. Flaherty was described as an "easy going, unassuming former Pittsburgh mayor whose cost-cutting measure had included 'turning in the mayor's Cadillac for a Dodge' [and Thornburgh was seen as] the 'steely-eyed prosecutor ... big time crime buster ... [and] cold-blooded crusader'" (Evidence, p. 89). Hard work was ahead as the campaign entered the summer of 1978 and schedulers booked Thornburgh everywhere they could. There were long days of breakfasts, luncheons, dinners, picnics, rallies, news conferences, editorial board meetings, and one-on-one sessions. "Ginny and I confided that our bottom-line goal was simply to avoid a humiliating defeat" (Evidence, p. 90).
  However, Jay Waldman presented to Dick Thornburgh, on July 7, a "strategic campaign plan that we were to follow to victory" (Evidence, p. 90), one embracing an "Eastern [Pennsylvania] strategy." This was scrupulously followed as the campaign slowly but surely gathered major endorsements, Thornburgh became increasingly recognized in voter-rich eastern Pennsylvania, his carefully researched and strategic issues found their marks, and Flaherty's cost cutting image came under question: "Did Flaherty Save Pittsburgh, or Bring it to its Knees?"
  As underdog, Thornburgh had agitated for debates and agreed upon two dates in the fall. Needless to say the stakes were high as the election neared and Thornburgh's research team prepared a massive binder of responses to every question that might conceivably be raised. Also included are likely responses of Flaherty and Thornburgh's potential responses to even those, all of which are included in the collection, for both debates.
  On October 10, the date the first debate was taped, "Flaherty surprised everyone by appearing in his shirtsleeves, apparently to enhance his 'man of the people' image ... our team was, on the whole, satisfied with the outcome. Most stories identified [Thornburgh] as the aggressor and highlighted Flaherty's admission regarding tax increases" (Evidence, p. 96).
  Meanwhile the candidates for Lieutenant Governor were coming under scrutiny. Bill Scranton was out on the campaign trail, well informed, and serving as a real asset to the election efforts. Democrat Bob Casey, the Pittsburgh schoolteacher, with precisely the same name as the Auditor General who sought primary selection as candidate for Governor, was creating major controversy for the Flaherty campaign: "'Like what do we need special teachers for the hearing-disabled. Put those kids at the front of the classroom if they can't hear'" (Evidence, p. 97).
  A significant endorsement came from the Philadelphia Daily News on October 25th, the date of the second debate. "Flaherty wore his suit coat this time ... no new ground was broken ... [and] as one observer noted: 'Overall, we would guess that Thornburgh gained the most from the televised debate ... Most viewers probably were impressed by Thornburgh's ease and confidence as he presented his arguments'" (Evidence draft, p. 314).
  Best of all was the post-debate news that the Pittsburgh Post Gazette had endorsed the Thornburgh/Scranton ticket and two days later, "the new Gallup poll showed that the margin among likely voters had shrunk to 4 percent - Flaherty 49 percent, Thornburgh 45" (Evidence, p. 97). Momentum was further evident, on October 29, by a "triple play" with all three of the remaining newspapers in Pittsburgh and Philadelphia endorsing Thornburgh/Scranton. By the beginning of November, Thornburgh/Scranton had twenty-five newspaper endorsements from across Pennsylvania, and Flaherty had only two. All the endorsements, for both tickets, are included in the archive and serve as a fascinating account of the campaigns and the candidates as Election Day neared.
  "As the campaign drew to a close, Ginny and I shared a plane back to Pittsburgh with reporters Tom Ferrick, Jr. from the Philadelphia Inquirer and Bob Dvorchak from the Associated Press. Both had been with us through thick and thin ... I asked them who they expected to win. One of them replied, 'Well, you've run a helluva race. You've made up a lot of ground and given Pete a real run for his money. But I don't think you're going to make it.' 'That's about how I see it,' I responded. But Ginny and I knew how far we had come and hoped against hope that we could pull off a victory" (Evidence, p. 99).
  Anticipating a long election night wait, the news at 8:30 P.M. that "Walter Cronkite has just called you a winner" dumbfounded Thornburgh as he dressed at home. The family was gathered up for the trip to campaign election headquarters, where "pandemonium reigned. By 9:30, all three networks had called the election in our favor, and at 10:35, Pete Flaherty called to concede and offer his congratulations ... The dimensions of the victory were astonishing ... [and] our upset captured a good deal of national attention" (Evidence, p. 100).
  In addition to the campaign documents and ephemera, there are detailed files in the collection regarding the vigorous post-election transition period, directed by Rick Stafford. Not only was there the matter of careful selection of the cabinet, in itself a challenging task, but also the opportunity to create study teams to assess issues, problems and needs in the various departments of state government. The study team reports are included in the collection and provide significant insight into priority areas identified for the new administration.
  The inaugural plans and events are fully documented in the collection and include a video of the inauguration which is available here online. Thornburgh's inaugural address, he states, "... was to be the most important that I had ever delivered and I spent an uncommon amount of time preparing it" (Evidence draft, p. 333).
  Thornburgh further states, "I set out what I felt to be the 'spirit of Pennsylvania.' ... While I noted 'a saddening loss of belief in the ability of government and its leaders to serve the people,' I stated that people wanted to believe in their government. What was needed, I said, was 'strong, effective and forthright leadership.' This I promised to provide, together with hard work, integrity, frugality, and 'a sense of humanity that is blind to race and roots, to sex and color, but is mindful of political injustice and human need'" (Evidence, p. 104).
  There are twelve sections of detailed campaign files: Speeches and Testimony; News Releases; Endorsements, Responses, and Articles; Campaign in Progress; Issue Research; Opposition Research; Planning Documents and Memoranda; Campaign Name Files; Dickman Files and Polls; Candidate Thornburgh's Files; Chron Files and News Clippings; Transition and Inaugural.
  Of special interest to researchers will be the five scrapbooks assembled after the campaign, which track it in content as well as in the media. These were undertaken at the request of the candidate, immediately post election, and, in fact, contain some material not available elsewhere, particularly some staff notes and memoranda. These are both colorful and informative and include issues, media coverage, internal campaign staff comments and notes, as well as campaign ephemera. These scrapbooks have been reformatted for preservation purposes. All collection scrapbooks are enumerated in Section 21.
  - Speeches, 1.
    The 1978 Campaign for Governor speeches are chronologically ordered. They include all major speeches given by Dick Thornburgh and testimony presented to various committees of the State Legislature. In addition to a "clean copy" of each speech, there also may be one or more drafts with notes, comments and changes. In addition, there may be "background material," with related newspaper articles, and speeches or notes on the same subject. Full text of all speeches and testimony is available here online.
    - "Government and its Citizens: Partners in Justice Law Day," Annual Law Day Luncheon of the York County Bar Association, York, PA, May 2, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - "Healthy Skepticism: The Graduate's Challenge," Point Park College, Soldiers and Sailors Memorial Hall, Pittsburgh, PA, May 14, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Testimony of Richard Thornburgh on Organized Crime and Official Corruption, Judiciary Committee of Pennsylvania, House of Representatives, Harrisburg, PA, May 19, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Graduation Address to the Duquesne University School of Law, Pittsburgh, PA, June 5, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - Statement before House Consumer Affairs Committee, House of Representatives, regarding Pennsylvania Antitrust Act, clean copy, October 28, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - "The Republican Challenge in Pennsylvania," Republican City Committee Dinner Meeting, Bethlehem, PA, November 1, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - "Wanted: An Environment for Jobs and Economic Growth in Pennsylvania," Pittsburgh Rotary Club, Pittsburgh, PA, December 14, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - Speech announcing his Candidacy for the 1978 Republican Nomination for Governor of Pennsylvania, Pittsburgh, Harrisburg, Philadelphia, PA, January 10, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - "State Government and the Appropriate Climate for Business and Industry in Pennsylvania," Central Pennsylvania Chapter of National Association of Accountants, State College, PA, January 18, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - "The Role of the Governor," Penn State University Political Science Seminar, Middletown, PA, March 17, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - "The Need for a State Energy Policy," Pennsylvania 1978 Consumer's Energy Conference, Hershey, PA, April 4, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - "Facing Up to the Highway and Bridge Crisis in Pennsylvania," Thornburg Bridge, Allegheny County, PA, April 7, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - "Pennsylvania's Great Northwest," Conewango Club, Warren, PA, April 10, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 13)
    - Pennsylvania League of Cities, Philadelphia 79th Annual Convention, Philadelphia, PA, April 17, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 14)
    - "Proposals for Ethics Legislation," Testimony to Special Senate Subcommittee on Ethics, Harrisburg, PA, April 19, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 15)
    - "Creating a Climate for Jobs in Pennsylvania," Thornburgh for Governor Committee Lawyers' Luncheon, Pittsburgh, PA, April 25, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 16)
    - "Education: An Investment in Pennsylvania's Future," a policy statement, Hershey, PA, May 2, 1978 (Box 56, Folder 17)
    - "The Challenge of Crime in Pennsylvania," a policy statement, Philadelphia, PA, May 9, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - "Growth, Opportunity, and Security: Commitment to Pennsylvania Human Services," Scranton, PA, May 15, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Position papers: Candidacy announcement, "The Role of Governor," "Highway and Bridge Crisis," "Creating a Climate for Jobs," "Education: Investment in Pennsylvania's Future," "Challenge of Crime," "Growth, Opportunity, Security: Human Services", undated (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Pennsylvania Mayor's Association National Convention, Grantsville, PA, July 18, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Testimony of Thornburgh and Scranton on Ethics Legislation, Sub-committee on Ethics of the State Government Committee of Pennsylvania, House of Representatives, Harrisburg, PA, August 29, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - "Pennsylvania At Work: A Labor Day Policy Statement", September 4, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - "Making Pennsylvania Proud Again: What People of the Commonwealth May Expect of a Thornburgh-Scranton Administration", September 15, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - "Visions for a Better Pennsylvania," Pennsylvania Newspaper Publishers' Association, Pittsburgh, PA, September 29, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 8)
    - Governor-elect Richard Thornburgh's remarks, Pennsylvania Society Dinner, New York, NY, December 9, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 9)
    - Inaugural Address, State Capitol, Harrisburg, PA, January 16, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 10)
  - News Releases, 2.
    The 1978 Campaign for Governor news releases are chronologically ordered. They include all news releases issued during the years 1977-1979, ranging from those preceding Thornburgh's official announcement of his candidacy, January 10, 1978, on through the post-election period as Governor-elect. Some release files include related background or supplemental material. There are a few undated news releases from the campaign and one folder containing releases apparently not issued. Full text of all news releases is available here online.
    - March 31, 1977-October 27, 1977 (Box 57, Folder 11)
      - "Crisis in integrity in PA," Mt. Lebanon Republican Committee and Council of Republican Women, March 31, 1977; 1.
      - FBI crime statistics for 1976 show "turning of the corner in crime-fighting efforts," Pittsburgh Chapter of Association for Systems Management, April 12, 1977; 2.
      - Shapp should set up "dry cleaning squad" in State's Justice Department to flush out crime and corruption in his administration, Republican leaders in Southwest PA, Greene County, April 13, 1977; 3.
      - Will be visiting lecturer on criminal law at University of Iowa School of Law, Iowa City, IA, April 14, 1977; 4.
      - State efforts against PA politico-racket complex woefully inadequate, Governor's Justice Commission Hearing at Allegheny County Courthouse, April 18, 1977; 5.
      - Partisan politics has no place in law enforcement, Pittsburgh Chapter of Society of Former Special Agents of FBI, April 28, 1977; 6.
      - True cost of PA's widespread corruption cannot be measured by statistics, Rotary Club, McKees Rocks and East Hills (44 Republican Club), May 5, 1977; 7.
      - Thornburgh urged investigation of Shapp political-financial house of cards, May 11, 1977; 8.
      - "The Stake of Business in Government Integrity," Erie Rotary Club, May 18, 1977; 9.
      - Traffic and Transportation Association of Pittsburgh regarding PennDOT's political management, May 20, 1977; 10.
      - Pennsylvanians are beginning to demand changes in old political ways, Legislative Committee of Greater Latrobe Chamber of Commerce, May 23, 1977; 11.
      - Attack on Shapp's nomination of Begler to PA Turnpike Commission, PA Association of Personnel Services, June 23, 1977; 12.
      - PA's future depends upon creation and nurturing of a sound economic climate, Lower Bucks County Chamber of Commerce, June 25, 1977; 13.
      - Advocated "zero-based politics," Oakland Kiwanis, July 5, 1977; 15.
      - House investigators into organized crime and official corruption in PA should recommend adoption of crime-fighting tools proved effective in federal efforts, Harrisburg Rotary Club, July 11, 1977; 16.
      - Firm crackdown on welfare-fraud termed "a truly humanitarian undertaking," Third Regional Conference of the National Welfare Fraud Association, July 12, 1977; 17.
      - PA's disastrous budget crisis linked to corruption and incompetence of Shapp administration, August 24, 1977; 18.
      - PA does not need new gun control laws, Elk County Republicans, October 22, 1977; 19.
    - January-March, 1978 (Box 57, Folder 12)
      - Announcement schedule, January 10, 1978; 1.
      - Formally announced his candidacy for the Republican nomination for Governor of PA, Pittsburgh, PA, January 10, 1978; 2.
      - Announced that he has named Penrose (Penny) Hallowell, a leading Bucks County farmer and conservationist as state Chairman of the PA Farmers for Thornburgh Committee, Doylestown, PA, February 9, 1978; 3.
      - Announced that William D. Ruckelshaus, former Deputy Attorney General of the U.S. and FBI Director, will be the featured speaker at his Philadelphia fundraising dinner and reception at the Franklin Institute on March 27, February 22, 1978; 4.
      - A luncheon honoring Republican gubernatorial candidate Dick Thornburgh will be held March 7th in Philadelphia and will feature as guest speaker former U.S. Attorney General, Harold R. Tyler, February 23, 1978; 5.
      - Will host a question and answer forum that is open to the public, March 8, at the Bucks County Community College in Newtown, March 3, 1978; 6.
      - Announced a program for combating corruption in government, Philadelphia, PA, March 7, 1978; 7.
      - Became first Republican candidate for governor to make a full and detailed personal financial disclosure, including his family's federal income tax returns for the past five years, March 9, 1978; 8.
      - Called on the PA House of Representatives to provide $100,000 needed for the continuation of a special legislative subcommittee's investigation of organized crime and corruption, March 14, 1978; 9.